<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Scotland being two copies, the one, a proclamation of the king: the other a protestation against it, by the noble men, barons: &amp; ministers of Scotland, both published at Edenburrough the 22 day of Febr: 1638</title>
            <title>Newes from Scotland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841858</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841858</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Scotland being two copies, the one, a proclamation of the king: the other a protestation against it, by the noble men, barons: &amp; ministers of Scotland, both published at Edenburrough the 22 day of Febr: 1638</title>
                  <title>Newes from Scotland.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richt Right Press,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:6473:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6473:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>NE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES</hi> FROM SCOTLAND Being two Copies, the one, a <hi>proclamation</hi> of the king: the other <hi>a proteſtation</hi> againſt it, by the <hi>Noble men, Barons:</hi> &amp; <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> both publiſhed at <hi>Edenburrough</hi> the 22 day of <hi>Febr:</hi> 1638</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES &amp;c.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>For ſoe much as vvee</hi> out of our princely care of maintaning the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion all ready profeſſed, and ſo beating downe all ſuperſtition: Having ordained a booke of common prayer to bee compiled for the generall and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall vſe and edification of our ſubjects within our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient kingdome of Scotland, the ſame being accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly don. In the framing whereof we tooke great care and paines ſo that there is nothing paſt therein but what was ſeen and approved by vs before the ſame was divulgated or printed: aſſuring all our loving ſubjects that not only our intention is, but even this very booke a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy meanes to maintaine the true religion allready profeſſed, and beat out all ſuperſtition, of which wee in our owne time doe not doubt but in a faire courſe to ſatisfie the iudgments of our good ſubjects: But having ſeen and conſidered ſome petitions and declarations given into our counſell againſt the ſaid Booke and late CANNONS of the booke, find our regall authority much iniured thereby, both in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the carrage, whereby wee certefie theſe of the Nobility, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Barrons Miniſters and others who have kept &amp; aſſiſted thoſe mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and convocations for contriving and ſubſcribing of the ſaid peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to bee liable to our high cenſure, both in their perſons and fortunes, they having conveyned themſelves without our conſent or authority: Yet becauſe wee beleeve that they have done herein on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of a prepoſterous zeale, and without any diſloyalty or diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Soueraingty: Our gratious plea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure (ſo farr as concernes thoſe meetings for conſulting and ſubſcribing of the ſaid petitions or preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame to any iudge or iudges within this kingdom) is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe therewith, and with what may bee the fault or error therein, to all ſuch as vpon ſignification or declaration of this our pleaſure, ſhall retein themſelves as become good and dutifull ſubjects. To which purpoſe OVR WILL is henceforth, and we charge you ſtreaghtly and commaund that incontimently theſe our letters ſeen, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and in our name and authority proclamation thereof bee made to all our leige ſubiects in all places needefull; that ſo <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hereof, and therewithall in our name and authority that ye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb facs="tcp:6473:2"/>all ſuch convocations and meetings in time to come, vnder the penalty of treaſon and alſo that ye command, charge and inhibit all our leiges and ſubjects, that none of them on any hand preſume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort or repaire to the Burrough of Starling, nor to any other Burrough, where our counſell and Seſſion ſits, till firſt they declare the cauſe of their comming to our counſell, and declare their warrant to that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: And further that wee commaund and charge all and ſundrie <hi>Provoſts, Bayleifes,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> within their bourroughs that they, &amp; every one of them have a ſpeciall care &amp; regard, to ſee this our <hi>royall will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> readyly &amp; dutifully obſerved in all points, and that noe violence be ſuffered within your bounds, vnder all the higheſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, crime or offence that they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit againſt us in that behalfe: And alſo that ye cammaund and charge all &amp; ſundry <hi>Noblemen,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> who are not actuall indwellers within the Burrough, neither are of number of the privy counſell and Seſſion; and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, and are already within this Burrough: that they and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of them remoue themſelves, and depart and paſſe forth of the ſaid Burrough (and not returne againe without the ſaid warrant) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of ſix houres after the publication hereof, vnder the ſaid penaltie of treaſon: And as concerning any petitions that ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after bee given to vs, upon this or any other ſubject: wee are likewiſe pleaſed to declare that we will not ſhut our eares there from: ſoe it bee not preiudiciall to our royall authoritie.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at ſtarling vnder our ſignet <date>the 19 of Febr. 1638</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Per actum Dominorum Conſilij.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> KINGS PROCLAMATION <hi>Being</hi> Proclaimed, the protestation here follovving against it, vvas at the ſame inſtance in the open ſtreet pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly read.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE the Noble men, Barons and Miniſters appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to attend his <hi>maieſties</hi> anſwere unto our humble petitions, and to preſent our greeuiances, and to doe what elſe might lawfully conduce to our humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. Did upon the 13 of <hi>September</hi> laſt, preſent one ſupplication to your <hi>Lordſhips;</hi> and another upon the 18 of <hi>October</hi> following: as alſo a new bill relativelie to the former in <hi>December</hi> after the 19 day.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6473:2"/>
            <p> In all which, we humbly remonſtrated, our iuſt exceptions againſt the Service <hi>booke,</hi> and <hi>Booke of Cannons, Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of this kingdome, as the contrivers, meanteaners and urgers thereof; and againſt their ſitting as our Iudges untill the cauſes betweene them and vs be decided.</p>
            <p>And withall we earneſtly ſupplicated to be ridd and delivered from theſe evils, and from all other innovations of that kind, introducted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the laudable lawes of this kingdome: as namely that of the <hi>high Commſſion</hi> and other evils particularly and generally mentioned in our ſupplications and complaints: And that theſe our <hi>parties,</hi> delinquent againſt our religion and lawes might be taken order with, and theſe preſſing greeviances be redreſſed, according to the laws of this realme, as in our ſupplications we have more largely expreſſed, the which we gaue into your Lordſhips upon the 19 of December aforeſaid, againſt the Arch-biſhops and Biſhohs our <hi>parties,</hi> who by conſequence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither could be, nor may be our Iudges.</p>
            <p>Whereupon your Lordſhips declared by your act given at <hi>Dealkeeth</hi> the ſaid 19 of <hi>December,</hi> that you would preſent our petition to his maieſties royall conſideration, &amp; that without any prejudice to us the ſaid <hi>ſupplicants,</hi> and moreover that we ſhould bee heard, in time and place convenient, &amp; in the mean time we ſhould receaue no preiudice as the ſaid act it ſelfe teſtifies for vs.</p>
            <p>Now where as we your humble ſupplicants (with long patience and hope grounded upon ſundry promiſes) were exſpecting an anſwere vnto our fore named humble deſires, we underſtood of ſome direction from his maieſtie, to you the Lords of his highnes privy counſell, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our complaints: and upon the ſame admitted the conſulting &amp; iudging both, of our ſupplication, and the kings anſwere there to, vnto the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops our direct <hi>par-ties:</hi> Contrary to our Proteſtation given in at Dealkeeth, and ſince renued at Starling: and contrary to your Lordſhips foreſaid act made at Dealkeeth.</p>
            <p>Leaſt therefore our ſilence ſhould bee preiudiciall to this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate a cauſe, as concernes Gods glory and worſhip, our religion and ſaluation, the lawes and liberties of this kingdome: or deregatory to our former ſupplications and complaints: or in breife, not anſwerable to the truſt of our commiſſion: we are forced out of our bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God, our king and native cuntry to take inſtument in the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Clarkes hands (ſeeing your Lordſhips refuſe to admitt our Declimiter for remoueall theſe of our parties) &amp; to proteſt in manner following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Wee proteſt that we may &amp; ought to haue an immediate courſe to preſent our iuſt greeviances to out ſacred Soverainge, and in a legall way and manner to proſecute the ſame, before the ordinarie and competent iudges, civil or Eccleaſticall; without any offence either offred by vs, or taken by your Lordſhips.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6473:3"/>
               <item> 2. Wee proteſt that the Arch-biſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Biſhops the parties whome we complaine vpon, cannot bee reputed or eſteemed lawfull iudges, to ſit in indicatory within this kingdome civill or Eccleſiaſticall, upon any of vs the ſaid ſupplicants, untill they doe by lawfull triall iudiciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purge themſelves of ſuch crimes as we have already laid to their charge: offering our ſelves to prove the ſame whenſoever his maieſtie ſhalbe pleaſed to giue us audience.</item>
               <item>3. Wee proteſt that no act or proclamation, whether paid or here after ſhall paſſe, in the counſell, and by the ſtates of Archb. and Biſhops (our parties and whome we haue declyned to be our Iudges) ſhall in no wiſe bee preiudiciall to vs, that is, either to our perſons, our lawfull meetings, proceedings and perſuits.</item>
               <item>4. Wee proteſt that neither our ſelves, nor any others, whoſe hearts the Lord ſhall moue to ioyne with vs in our ſupplications againſt the aforeſaid innovocations, ſhall incurre any danger, either in life, lands, or any politicall or Eccleſiaſticall penaltie: For not obſerving ſuch acts, Bookes, Canons, Writts, judicatories and proclamations introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced without, or againſt the acts of parliament, or ſtatutes of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But it ſhalbe lawfull for us and them to vſe our ſelves in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion, or the externall worſhip of God, and policie of the Church; according to the word of God, and the laudable conſtitutions of this Church and kingdome.</item>
               <item>5. Seeing all ſuch as have taken theſe innovations to heart, have by a legal and ſubmiſſive way of ſupplications ſought redreſſe and been calme and quiet in hope of reformation: Wee proteſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for that if inconvenience ſhall happen to fal out (which we pray God to prevent) vpon the preſſing of the ſaid innovations or evils, generally and ſpecially mentioned in our former complaints, and vpon your Lordſhips refuſall, to take order for redreſſe. That the ſame ſhall not be imputed unto us, who moſt humbly deſire to have all things redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by order.</item>
               <item>6. We proteſt before God, the Heavens, and the Angels, that theſe our Requeſts (proceeding from conſcience, and our due reſpect to his Majeſties honour) doe tend to no other end, but to the preſervation of the true reformed religion, the Lawes &amp; Liberties of his Majeſties moſt ancient Kingdome, and the ſatisfaction of our humble deſires contained in our ſupplications, according to his Majeſties goodneſſe and juſtice; From whom we doe certainly exſpect, that his ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will proceed and grant remedy to our juſt petions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints: as may be exſpected from ſo gracious a King towards his loyall and dutifull Subjects, calling for redreſſe of ſo oppreſſing gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, praying hartily that his Majeſtie may long and proſperouſly raigne over us.</item>
            </list>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6473:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
